A Guide to the Virginia Constitutional Convention (1901-1902), Records, 1901-1902
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1901-1902
Library of Virginia
20936, 23877c and 40664
4.91 cubic feet and 1 volume
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Judge Daniel Ginnan, 4 February 1935 (accession 20936) Transferred from the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 16 October 1952 (accession 23877c) Acquision information unknown, prior to 1905 (accession 40664)
Historical Information
Many Virginians felt that the constitution approved in 1869 had been forced upon them and over the next several years, especially after military Reconstruction ended, there was a movement to call a new convention. A number of acts were passed by the General Assembly putting the question to the voters, who always voted in the negative. By the turn of the century, however, there were other reasons behind the demand for a new constitution: the inadequacies of the state government in regulating the railroad and public utility companies that had become increasingly politically powerful in the postwar period, the expense of administering the government and judicial system, and the desire on the part of political conservatives to disenfranchise black voters. An enabling act was approved by the voters in May 1900 and elections for delegates were held in May 1901.
The delegates assembled on 12 June 1901, and most of the preliminary work was done in committees selected to study specific topics. The committee reports and recommendations were then debated by the full convention. The new constitution established a poll tax as a prerequisite for voting, effectively disenfranchising black voters, revamped the judicial system and created the State Corporation Commission. The convention adjourned on 26 June 1902, and shortly thereafter proclaimed the new constitution to be in force on 10 July 1902, without allowing voters to ratify it. This unorthodox procedure was approved by the governor and the General Assembly, as well as the state Supreme Court of Appeals.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the records of the Virginia Constitutional Convention (1901-1902). Included are committee minute books, convention minute books, committee records, oaths of office required by 1902 Constitutions, pay roll books and drafts of the constitution and the original, approved constitution.
The committee minute books record the activities of each committee and also include an attendance roll listing which committee members were present. (Volume 1) Committee on Education and Public Instruction, 1901 June 27 - 1902 January 28. (Volume 2) Committee on Public Instructions and Prisons, 1901 June 27 - November 21. (Volume 3) Committee on Final Revision and Adjustments of the Various Provisions of the Constitution that may be agreed upon, and upon the Schedule, 1902 January 31 - April 24. (Volume 4) Committee on the Legislative Department, Except Such Matters as come within the Jurisdiction of other Standing Committees, 1901 (lists only action of committee). (Volume 5) Committee on Taxation and Finance, 1901 June 27 - 1902 January 29. (Volume 6) Committee on the Organization and Government of Cities and Towns, 1901 June 29 - 1902 January 9. (Volume 7) Committee on Privileges and Elections, 1901 June 21 - September 12 (Volume 8) Committee on the Judiciary, 1901 June 26 - November 20; and Committee on Agriculture, Manufacturing and Industrial Interests and Immigration, 1901 July 31 - 1902 January 8. (Volume 9) Committee on Preamble and Bill of Rights, the Division of Governmental Powers, and on such portions of the Constitution as shall not be referred to other Committees, 1901 June 28 - 1902 January 29. (Volume 10) Committee on the Elective Franchise, Qualifications for Office, Basis of Representation and Apportionment, and on Elections, 1901 June 27 - August 27. (Volume 11) Committee on Reduction of Expenses, 1901 June 27 - September 11. (Volume 12) Committee on the Organization and Government of Counties, 1901 July 2 - November 11. (Volume 13) Committee on Rules, Accounts and Expenditures, Journal and Enrollment, Minor Committees, 1901-1902.
The Convention Minute Books chronicle the daily activities of the Convention between 1901 June 22 and 1902 June 5. Also included is a volume documenting the Conventions work as the Committee of the Whole between 1901 July 29 and 1902 June 26. (Volume 14) Minutes of the Convention from 1901 June 22 and November 22. (Volume 15) Minutes of the Convention from 1901 November 23 and 1902 March 3. (Volume 16) Minutes of the Convention from 1902 March 4 to June 5. (Volume 17) Minutes of the Committee of the Whole of the Constitutional Convention from 1901 July 29 to 1902 June 26. Also included is a transcript of the minutes of proceedings of the Convention from 12-13 and 20-21 June 2001 (accession 20936).
The Committee Records include resolutions, reports, correspondence and petitions for the following committees: Committee on Education and Public Instruction Committee on Public Institutions and Prisons Committee on Corporations Also included are miscellaneous committee reports.
Oaths Required by 1902 Virginia State Constitution. Under the provisions of section 22 of the Schedule, the Constitution went into effect on 10 July 1902. On that date, at noon, the Governor qualified under the new Constitution by taking the oath to support the same. All other executive officers at the seat of government, the members of the Supreme Court of Appeals, judges of circuit, county, and corporation courts, qualified under the new Constitution from 10 July to 20 July, inclusive, the time allowed them in which to take the oath or vacate their respective offices. Oaths are arranged alphabetically by locality and by office.
Pay roll volumes - These volumes (1901 and 1902) list each delegate alphabetically and note payments for attendance and reimbursement for travel expenses.
Constitution of Virginia, 1901-1902. Four portfolios containing the Constitution of Virginia as revised by the Committee on Final Revision and Adjustment. Articles 1, 2, 3 and 4 (Sections 1-68 on pages 1-31) Articles 5, 6, 7 and 8 (Sections 69-128 on pages 31-63) Articles 9, 10, 11 and 12 (Sections 129-167 on pages 64-100) Articles 13, 14 and 15 (Sections 168-197 on pages 101-120), The Schedule (pages 121-131) and Registration Ordinance.
Also included is a corrected first draft of various articles of the Constitution, beginning with Article 7 on the organization and government of counties and the approved Constitution signed by members present (accession 23877c).
Arrangement
Series arranged by type of record.
Contents List
- Volume 1 - Committee on Education and Public Instruction, 1901 June 27 - 1902 January 28 (Box 1)
- Volume 2 - Committee on Public Instructions and Prisons, 1901 June 27 - November 21 (Box 1)
- Volume 3 - Committee on Final Revision and Adjustments of the Various Provisions of the Constitution that may be agreed upon, and upon the Schedule, 1902 January 31 - April 24 (Box 1)
- Volume 4 - Committee on the Legislative Department, Except such matters as come within the Jurisdiction of other Standing Committees, 1901 (lists only actions of committee) (Box 2)
- Volume 5 - Committee on Taxation and Finance, 1901 June 27 - 1902 January 29 (Box 2)
- Volume 6 - Committee on the Organization and Government of Cities and Towns, 1901 June 29 - 1902 January 9 (Box 2)
- Volume 7 - Committee on Privileges and Elections, 1901 June 21 - September 12 (Box 3)
- Volume 8 - Committee on the Judiciary, 1901 June 26-November 20; and Committee on Agriculture, Manufacturing and Industrial Interests and Immigration, 1901 July 31-1902 January 8 (Box 3)
- Volume 9 - Committee on Preamble and Bill of Rights, the Division of Governmental Powers, and on such portions of the Constitution as shall not be referred to other Committees, 1901 June28-1902 January 29 (Box 3)
- Volume 10 - Committee on the Elective Franchise, Qualifications for Office, Basis of Representation and Apportionment, and on Elections, 1901 June 27-August 27 (Box 4)
- Volume 12 - Committee on the Organization and Government of Counties, 1901 July 2-November 11 (Box 4)
- (Box 4)
- Volume 11 - Committee on Reduction of Expenses, 1901 June 27-September 11
- Volume 14 - Minutes of the Convention from 1901 June 22 to November 22 (Box 5)
- Volume 15 - Minutes of the Convention from 1901 November 23 to 1902 March 3 (Box 5)
- Volume 16 - Minutes of the Convention from 1902 March 4 to June 5 (Box 5)
- Volume 17 - Minutes of the Committee of the Whole of the Constitutional Convention from 1901 July 29 to 1902 June 26 (Box 5)
- Committee Records - Committee on Education and Public Instruction, Resolutions (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Committee Records - Committee on Education and Public Instruction, Reports (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Committee Records - Committee on Education and Public Instruction, Correspondence, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Committee Records - Committee on Education and Public Instruction, Petitions and Resolutions (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Committee Records - Committee on Education and Public Instruction, Speech of Giles B. Jackson, Secretary of the Negro Business League of Virginia before the Committee, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Committee Records - Committee on Public Institutions and Prisons, Resolutions (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Committee Records - Committee on Public Institutions and Prisons, Reports (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Committee Records - Committee on Public Institutions and Prisons, Correspondence, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Committee Records - Committee on Public Institutions and Prisons, MIscellaneous Records (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Committee Records - Committee on Corporations, Resolutions (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Committee Records - Committee on Corporations, Correspondence, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Committee Records - Miscellaneous Committee Reports (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Oaths - Supreme Court of Appeals (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Oaths - Circuit Court (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Oaths - County Court, Accomack-Lunenburg Counties (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Oaths - County/Corporation Courts, Mathews County - Winchester (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Oaths - State Office Holders (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Minutes of the Convention, 12-13 and 20-21 June 1901 (accession 20936) (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Volume - Pay Roll, Virginia Constitutional Convention, 1901 (Box 8)
- Volume - Pay Roll, Virginia Constitutional Convention, 1902 (Box 8)
- Portfolio - Constitution of Virginia, Articles 1-4 (Sections 1-68 on pages 1-31) (Box 9)
- Portfolio - Constitution of Virginia, Articles 5-8 (Sections 69-128 on pages 31-63) (Box 9)
- Portfolio - Constitution of Virginia, Articles 9-12 (Sections 129-167 on pages 64-100) (Box 9)
- Portfolio - Constitution of Virginia, Articles 13-15 (Sections 168-197 on pages 101-120), The Schedule (pages 121-131) and Registration Ordinance (Box 9)
- Corrected first draft of various articles of the Constitution, beginning with Article 7 on the organization and government of counties (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Volume - Constitution of Virginia....proclaimed in convention on 6 June 1902, signed by members present (accession 23877c) (Box 11)